Guide to the Brooke Astor Papers 1884-2007 MS 3157
New-York Historical Society
Brooke Astor papers
1884-2007
New-York Historical Society
Astor, Brooke
MS 3157
8 Linear feet in 7 boxes + 1 oversize folder
The collection includes personal papers and photographs of the socialite and philanthropist Brooke Astor, as well as some documents concerning her parents, other family members, and her husbands, especially Vincent Astor. Correspondence and photographs, mostly from the 1970s-2002, reflect Brooke Astor's social and philanthropic connections. The collection also holds some of Brooke's diaries and other writings, and family photographs, including an album dating from Brooke's father's tenure as a U.S. Marine in Hawaii and in China. Her father's time as American High Commissioner in Haiti in the 1920s is represented by a set of letters written by Brooke's mother from Port-au-Prince.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in 5 series:
Series I. Family Papers, 1884-2002
Series II. General Correspondence, 1953-2002, 2007
Series III. Writings by and about Brooke Astor, 1915-2005
Series IV. Photographs, circa 1885-2007
Series V. Memorabilia, 1956-2007, undated
Biographical / Historical
Brooke Astor (then Roberta Brooke Russell) was born in 1902 in New Hampshire to John Henry Russell Jr. (1872-1947) and Mabel Cecile Hornby Howard Russell (1879–1967). John Russell joined the U.S. Marine Corps in 1894 and certain of his career postings pertain to documents in the collection and to Brooke's life. In particular, John Russell was stationed (with his family) in Honolulu, Hawaii, during Brooke's early childhood; in China during Brooke's early teenage years; and in Haiti during the U.S. occupation of that country, where the adult Brooke apparently visited. Brooke would document her recollections of her early years in a 1962 book "Patchwork Child."
Brooke married at the age of 17, in 1919, to John Dryden Kuser (who went by the call name "Dryden"), the son of a wealthy New Jersey businessman. They had one son, Anthony, but the marriage was an unhappy one, ending in divorce in 1930. Brooke married a second time, in 1932, to Charles "Buddy" Marshall. It was a happy marriage and Brooke Marshall's son by Dryden Kuser, Anthony, eventually took Marshall as his surname. During this marriage, in the 1940s, Brooke worked as an editor for House & Garden magazine. Marshall died in 1952 and Brooke married a third time, in 1953, to William Vincent Astor, taking the name Brooke Astor. Brooke recounted these marriages and more of her life in her 1980 memoir "Footprints."
Vincent Astor (he seems generally not to have used William) was a member of the wealthy Astor family. His father, John Jacob Astor IV, died in 1912 on the Titanic, leaving a fortune to Vincent, who left Harvard to pursue business and philanthropic interests with his riches. Vincent served with the Navy in both World War I and World War II, and even his yachts were re-purposed by the Coast Guard for military duty. Brooke was Vincent's third wife, and perhaps anticipating that his life would be short, engaged her in his philanthropic endeavors through the Vincent Astor Foundation. Vincent died in 1959, leaving the substance of his estate to Brooke, who also controlled the Foundation. For the last decades of her life, Brooke Astor pursued her philanthropic interests, among them the New York Public Library, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, the New York Zoological Society, and others. Brooke Astor died in 2007 at the age of 105.
(The above note was based on various on-line sources, including Wikipedia.)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charlene Marshall, 2019
Scope and Contents
The collection includes personal papers and photographs of the socialite and philanthropist Brooke Astor, as well as some documents concerning her parents, other family members, and her husbands. Papers related specifically to Brooke include correspondence, mostly from the 1970s-2002, reflecting her social connections with the extended Astor family, leaders of cultural and religious institutions in New York City, and other prominent people. Much of this correspondence is social in nature, with pleasantries, courtesies, invitations, acknowledgements of gifts, and other such matters. There are many photographs in the collection, also from the 1970s-early 2000s, that similarly reflect Astor's social and philanthropic circles.
Brooke Astor's literary and artistic aspirations reaching back to her youth are documented in the collection with short essays, poetry and fiction, as well as photograph transparencies of drawings. Diary entries from 1915-17, when Brooke Russell was a teenager, and transcripts of interviews from the 1990s with the elderly Brooke Astor, bookend the writings by and about her. A dinner party record from 1937-41 and photographs from the first half of the twentieth century give glimpses into Brooke's life during that time, including photos of her second husband, Charles Marshall, and third husband, Vincent Astor. Glimpses into Vincent's life and career are also represented in the collection with documents recognizing his contributions with the U.S. Navy in World War II, a detailed appraisal of his country estate Ferncliff, his probated will, and some photographs and other documents.
The collection also holds several documents relating to Brooke's parents and grandparents. Among these are a bound volume of letters written by Brooke's mother, Mabel Russell, from Haiti in 1923-27 where she lived during the tenure of her husband, John H. Russell Jr., as American High Commissioner. A photograph album dating from about 1912 includes photographs from Honolulu and China, where John Russell was stationed at the time, and several of these photographs depict Brooke and her family. Family history papers in the collection also include several letters from the 19th century authors Robert Traill Spence Lowell and Mary Lowell Putnam to Brooke's maternal grandparents.
Haiti -- Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century.; Associations, institutions, etc. -- New York (State) -- New York.; Philanthropists.; Diaries.; Letters (correspondence); Manuscripts (documents); Photograph albums.; Photographs.; Astor, Vincent, 1891-1959; Lowell, Robert, 1816-1891; Putnam, M. L. (Mary Lowell), 1810-1898; Russell, John H. (John Henry), 1872-1947
- Series I. Family Papers, 1884-2002; .75 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents
  The series holds documents that relate primarily to Brooke Astor's parents and other ancestors, family history, genealogy, her third husband, William Vincent Astor, and to a lesser extent, her second husband, Charles Marshall. The series includes letters from the 19th century authors Robert Traill Spence Lowell and Mary Lowell Putnam written to Brooke's maternal grandparents; letters written by Brooke's mother, Mabel Russell, from Haiti in 1923-27 where Mabel's husband, John Henry Russell Jr., was the American High Commissioner at the time during what is referred to as the United States' occupation of Haiti; and a 1942 appraisal of Vincent Astor's estate, Ferncliff, in New York State; among other documents. The container list below provides further details on the contents.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged roughly by the family member that the documents principally relate to.
  - Genealogical and family history notes, 1943, 1982, undated (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
    The principal document is a notebook prepared by Brooke Astor (then Brooke Marshall) for her son, Anthony Marshall, in 1943. Includes a family tree on Brooke's maternal side, with transcribed notes about ancestors, the Carroll family and Robert Traill Spence. Also undated notes on the origin of the name Astor prepared by genealogist Henry Dudley Teeter, and a booklet "The History of Astor on the St. Johns, Astor Park" compiled by A. Wass de Czege (1982).
  - Letters from Mary Lowell Putnam, circa 1885-1890 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
    8 letters to George Howard and 1 to his wife, Roberta, (Brooke Astor's maternal grandparents) from Mary Lowell Putnam. The letters principally refer to family genealogy, exchanges of photographs, health, and references to George and Roberta's children, including Mabel, Brooke's mother.
  - Letters from Robert Traill Spence Lowell, 1884-1889 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
    8 letters to George H. Howard and 1 to George's wife, Roberta, or Bertie (Brooke Astor's maternal grandparents) from Robert Traill Spence Lowell (1816-1891). Subject matter includes references to the dedication of the Washington Monument, the incoming presidential administration, attempts to publish material, apparent distress over a marriage, death of Lowell's son, and other matters. One letter is dated 1844, but this seems clearly incorrect and is likely 1884.
  - Letters from other Lowells, 1885-1886, 1893 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
    2 letters from M.A. Lowell, one to George Howard, the other to his wife Roberta, or Bertie, with thanks for sending a poem and a card, travel plans or impediments on travel plans, health matters, and other family matters (1885-86). 1 letter from Rebecca R. Lowell to Roberta, declining Roberta's invitation to visit because of Rebecca's extensive travel conflicts.
  - Letter from Cousin Mary to Mabel [Howard/Russell], 1892 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
    1 letter (12 pages) to Brooke Astor's mother, referring to various children in the family.
  - Scrapbook "Dog and his various uses", circa 1914 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
    Small scrapbook with a few pictures of dogs being helpful in some way, notably in connection with World War I. Likely compiled by Brooke Astor when a child.
  - Charles H. Marshall documents, 1930, 1952 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
    Notice of Marshall's appointment as Secretary to the Special Commission for the Study and Review of Conditions in Haiti, confirmation of compensation, and authorization to proceed to Haiti (1930). Engrossed resolutions from the Board of Managers of the Seamen's Church Institute, with transmittal sympathy card, to Brooke at the death of Marshall (1952).
  - Letters from Mabel Russell to Mary, 1923 November-1927 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8a)
    One slip-cased volume of typed letters from Mabel (Brooke's mother) to a Mary. Most of the letters are written from Haiti, where Mabel's husband, John Henry Russell Jr., was the American High Commissioner to Haiti at the time during what is referred to as the United States' occupation of Haiti (1915-1934). Mabel's letters primarily relate to social engagements and social gossip among the Americans in Haiti, but also include references to travel around the country with positive comments on the economic development there; some Haitian politics; references to visits from family and friends (including Brooke and her first husband, Dryden Kuser); travels to Guantanamo, Cuba, and brief returns to the United States; etc. There are a small number of snapshots in the volume.
  - Note from Port-au-Prince, 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8b)
    A 2 page typescript, which appears to have been typed in circa 1990s-2000s, dated October 28, 1924 from Port-au-Prince, of notes on social matters. The writer is likely Mabel.
  - (William) Vincent Astor. Psalm book, 1902 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
    A small book of psalms, in Latin, wth notation at front: "psalms learned by heart" (1902).
  - (William) Vincent Astor. Certificates, 1918, 1924 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
    2 certificates: Astor's Navy Department certificate of commission as "Lieutenant (jg) (Line Duties Only) for temporary service," signed by Acting Secretary of the Navy Franklin D. Roosevelt (1918); and certificate of appointment of Lieutenant USNRF 2 (1924).
  - (William) Vincent Astor. Album, 1943-1945 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
    Album with documents recognizing Astor's service as Observation Craft Officer, Staff, Commander Eastern Sea Frontier, during World War II (photographs, letters, certificate, commendation).
  - (William) Vincent Astor. Property appraisal, 1942 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 12)
    Folder holds "Fire insurance valuation report on property of William Vincent Astor Estate, [Ferncliff], Rhinebeck, Dutchess County, New York." Prepared by Home Insurance Company for Edward M. Van Buren. Includes description of each building, approximate replacement value, 77 photos of the buildings, and diagrams. Because the snapshots of the buildings are glued into pages and can become disassociated with their typed captions on the book's page, the processing archivist numbered the captions in [brackets] and wrote the number in the margin of the corresponding photo.
  - Letters from Vincent Astor to Brooke, 1958 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 13)
    6 letters and telegrams sent to Brooke while she was in Rome, the "only time we were separated in our brief marriage" as Brooke penned on the envelope enclosure. The letters touch on some business, but are principally expressions of affection and updates on domestic matters.
  - Condolence letters re: Vincent Astor, 1959 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 14)
    Letters to Brooke Astor, including one from Clyde Tolson of the Federal Bureau of Investigation. Other condolence letters to Brooke can be found in various correspondence folders in Series II.
  - Vincent Astor will (3 folders), 1959, 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 15-17)
    The folders hold a photocopy of Vincent Astor's probated will (1959); letters, especially from Earl Newson & Company, concerning press notices about the contested will (1959); and unexecuted copies of a release with related estate account report by Bankers Trust (1991).
  - "Selected letters from Vincent to Brooke on the occasion of Brooke Astor's one hundredth birthday", 2002 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 18)
    2 copies (of 200 printed) of a booklet published by The Frick Collection in 2002. In addition to the text of letters, there are facsimiles of letters at the front of the volumes. Letters provided for reproduction by Brooke Astor's son, Anthony D. Marshall.
- Series II. General Correspondence, 1953-2002, 2007; .75 Linear feet
  The series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence to/from Brooke Astor. Much of the correspondence consists of courtesies and pleasantries: proposals to meet for a lunch, dinner, or other visit; acknowledgements of pleasant visits; congratulations to Brooke for her book "Footprints"; compliments on some achievement; thanks to Brooke for financial donations; expressions of gratitude for Brooke's participation as a trustee or other supporter of an institution (usually cultural or religious); birthday and holiday greetings; and the like. Many of the letters reflect a closer relationship, such as that of family or friend, between Brooke and her correspondent, and those letters often include references to shared experiences or common acquaintances. There are some condolence letters referring to the deaths of various acquaintances, including some to Brooke on the occasion of her husband, Vincent's, death in 1959; similar letters found together are in Series I.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. With some adjustments, this was the original order of the correspondence as received at N-YHS.
  - A. General, 1959-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1)
    Correspondents include, among others, Joe Armstrong, Nane Annan, Renata Adler, Lee & Walter Annenberg, and various Astors from England (Annabel, Pauline, Gavin, William, Jacqueline).
  - Ahern, Patrick (Bishop), 1980-1997 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 2)
  - Andrew, John G.B. (Reverend), 1983-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 3)
  - Astor, David (Oxford, England), 1981-2000 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 4)
  - Astor, Brooke (photocopies of outgoing letters), 1979-1998 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 5)
    Letters are to, among others, Joseph Alsop, Lady Wright (England), Edward M. Kennedy, James C.Y. Watt, Mrs. John Astor (England), Nigel Hawthorne (England), Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, Liz Smith, Vartan Gregorian, Winston Churchill (1997), U.S. President Bill Clinton (in support of the Municipal Art Society's proposal for use of the entire post office building for the proposed new Pennsylvania Station). Outgoing letters are also found in the various other correspondence files.
  - B. General, 1975-2000 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 6)
    Correspondents include, among others, Charles Baskerville, Mark Birley, Gioria Maroni Braga, and Mrs. William Francis (Pat) Buckley.
  - Birley, Rhoda, 1959-1963 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 7)
  - C. General, 1950s-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 8)
    Correspondents include, among others, Joan Ganz Cooney, Schuyler and Catia Chapin, Lord Carrington, U.S. Senator William S. Cohen, Helen Clay Chace, Cass Canfield, Douglass Campbell, Roland L. Redmond (on Carter, Ledyard & Milburn letterhead), Isaac Stern (on Carnegie Hall letterhead), Charles -- (Pierpont Morgan Library), and draft of letter for the Critical Choices Commission's Forty Under Forty conference.
  - Chase, Lynn, 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 9)
  - Curley, Walter J.P., 1986-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 10)
  - Prince Charles, 1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
    Holds a Christmas card with photo of Prince Charles and his sons on polo horses, and a handwritten letter expressing regret at not being able to meet with Brooke on her visit to England.
  - Clatsop County (Oregon) Historical Society, 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12)
  - D. General, 1959-1998 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 13)
    Correspondents include, among others, Douglas Dillon, David Dinkins (Mayor, New York) and Joyce B. Dinkins, Mary Dunn, John A. Drayton, Mrs. Angier Biddle (Robin) Duke, Ruth du Pont, Kate Davis, Jarmila Novotna Daubek, Frank L. Dent, and Eric Drake.
  - De la Renta, Annette, undated (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - E. General, 1968-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
    Correspondents include, among others, Charles Engelhard, and Archbishop Edward M. Egan.
  - Elliott, Eleanor T. (Elly) & Jock, 1980-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 16)
  - F. General, 1986-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 17)
    Correspondents include, among others, -- Fasciani (transmitting to Brooke a photocopy of a 1939 letter from Vincent Astor to Peter Isola re: a birthday cake), Barbara Fleischman, Pamela Fiori, and Ellen Futter.
  - G. General, 1953, 1980-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 18)
    Correspondents include, among others, Frances Guthrie, Henry Grunwald, Barbara Goldsmith, Henry Gillespie, Clare Gregorian, Donna Hanover Giuliani, Donald R. Gardner, Robert Hixon Glore (transmitting a photograph of a car he purchased in 1989 that was formerly owned by Vincent Astor), and Georgia -- (London).
  - Grein, Richard F. (Right Reverend, Bishop of New York), 1990-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 19)
  - H. General, 1959-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 20)
    Correspondents include, among others, Barbara Harper, Conrad Harper, Eleanor Howard, Clifford Henderson, Emily Harding, Marilyn Hewitt, August Heckscher, Donna Hanover, Becky Hamilton, Arthur A. Houghton, Jr., Gerald Heard, Mrs. Leland Hayward, Barklie McKee Henry, and Henry -- (Philadelphia). Also, the program for the memorial service for Leland Hayward (1971).
  - I and J. General, 1970-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 21)
    Correspondents include, among others, Invalids-at-Home (England), Grace Bristed Jackson, Jayne --, Jimmie -- (England).
  - K. General, 1978-1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 22)
    Correspondents include, among others, Edward I. Koch (Mayor, New York), Alfred Kornfeld, Walter Kaiser, and Hans Kornberg.
  - Kissinger, Henry & Nancy, 1987-1996 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23)
  - L. General, 1982-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 24)
    Correspondents include, among others, Barry M. Landau, Gertie Legendre, Paul Le Clerc, Carl Little, Joshua Lederberg, Laeticia Debon Compagna, and Liz--.
  - M. General, 1959-1997 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 25a)
    Correspondents include, among others, Clifford D. Mallory, Jr., Pauline Mallory, Judy Montague, Betsy F. Melcher, Mr. & Mrs. Gilbert Miller, Alma Morgan, Mab Molte, Mollie-- (Scotland), Rev. Paul Moore, Rev. Andrew C. Mead, Rev. James Parks Morton, Rev. Theodore E. McCarrick, Rev. Charles G. McDonagh, Municipal Art Society, and Museum of Modern Art.
  - Mary Rose Project (Society for the Archaeological Study of the Mary Rose), 1981-1982 (Offsite-box 2, Offsite-box 25b)
  - McEwen, Romana, 1983-1997 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 26)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1978-2002 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27a)
    Correspondents include, among others, John Pope-Hennessy, Douglas Dillon, Richard R. Morsches, Merribell Parsons, and Philippe de Montebello.
  - Middle East Trip, 1980-1981 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 27b)
    Holds itineraries, photographs with Omar Zawawi and Henry and Nancy Kissinger in Israel, thank you and related letters, and program.
  - N. General, 1972-1988 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 28)
    Correspondents include, among others, Richard Nixon (photocopy), Billy Norwid, Christian Norgren, Nin -- (London), New York University (James Hester), New York Public Library (Richard Couper), and New York Society Library (Spencer Byard).
  - New York Botanical Garden, 1994 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29a)
    Letters concerning Fordham University's intent to build a radio tower near NYBG: general letter from NYGB requesting support in opposing the tower and exchange between Brooke Astor and New York City Mayor Rudolph W. Giuliani regarding her opposition.
  - New York Zoological Society, 1970-1978 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 29b)
  - O and P. General, 1975-1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 30)
    Correspondents include, among others, Archbishop John Cardinal O'Connor, L. Jay Oliva (NYU), J.H. Plumb, Dave Peck, Mrs. Henry Parish II, Walter Persegati, and Peter Pierpont Adams.
  - R. General, 1959, 1969-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31a)
    Correspondents include, among others, Jane Russell, Happy Rockefeller, Khalil Riad Rizk, Casey Ribicoff, Selwa Roosevelt, Dillon Ripley(?), Arthur Ross, Mike Ryan, John Richardson (House & Garden), Frederick P. Rose, Carola Rothschild, and Lydia and Roland Redmond.
  - Random House, 1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 31b)
    Holds the orginal executed agreement for Brooke Astor's introduction to the Library of America's edition of "The House of Mirth."
  - RMS Titanic, Inc., 1995 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 32)
  - Rockefeller, David, 1983-2000 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 33)
  - Rockefeller, Laurance & Mary, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 34)
  - Rohatyn, Elizabeth, 1982-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 35)
  - S. General (2 folders), 1958-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 36-37)
    Correspondents include, among others, in the first folder: Lady Salter, Whitney Straight, Smithsonian (Dillon Ripley, David Challinor), Arthur Schlesinger, Jr., Martin E. Segal, Percy E. Sutton, John T. Sargent, Peggy Scholz, Stella Saltonstall, Lizzie --, Sullivan & Cromwell; in the second folder: Richard Salomon, Chauncey Stillman.
  - Marchioness of Salisbury (Marjorie "Mollie" Olein), 1988-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 38)
  - T. General, 1981-1996 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 39)
    Correspondents include, among others, Robert H. Thayer, Blaine Trump, and F. George Trescher, Jr.
  - Tree, Marietta, 1989-1991 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 40a)
    In addition to a letter and postcard from Tree, the folder holds Tree's obituary and an essay forwarded by Tree to Brooke: "Northeast Harbor, Maine" by Frances Fitzgerald.
  - U.S. Navy, 1974-2001 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 40b)
    Relates at least in part to the Vincent Astor Memorial Leadership Essay Award.
  - V. General, 1986-1992 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 41)
    Correspondents include, among others, Virginia House Settlement (restoration project), Peter F. Vallone, and Jean Vanderbilt.
  - W. General, 1959-1999 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 42)